Jinnah sahib what the princely states are joining with Pakistan,
what will they get from you?
Your highness I made my position very clear
I'm ready to give much higher status than India
and Your Highness, I'm signing a blank page
to join Pakistan, whatever demands you have
include them.
thank you Jinnah Sahib
if Jodhpur can join with Pakistan, then allow us to use Karachi port
free import of weapons and most importantly, with Jodhpur
your Sindh railway line to Hyderabad must be under our control
anything for you, Your Highness
Yuvraj
like Jodhpur, you will share border with us
like Jodhpur, isn't Jaisalmer not joining Pakistan?
we can join Pakistan, Jinnah Sahib
but we have a condition
anytime in our province
there is a fight between Hindus and Muslims
will you remain neutral?
what sort of question is this, Maharaja?
Hindus and Muslims fighting is a useless thought
Your Highness, as long as Central Govt in India is weak, we are both strong
I have signed on the dotted lines, you fill in the conditions
Im so grateful to Jinnah Sahib for such a big proposal
I... I.... I'll quickly think over & let you know my decision
Imagine what would've happened if creator of Pakistan, Md Ali Jinnah didnt withdraw the proposal...
India as we know today would've looked like this
This is that story of formation of India
which has never been told before.
Welcome to प्रधानमंत्री
Prime Minister, a program in which
we relate those stories
which were not written in any books
those stories of Free India
which not heard and not understood
we will not be able to understand our country fully
to start the first episode, lets go pre-independence
June 3, 1947
how will free India look like?
this issue was decided on that day
on June 3, 1947, Delhi All-India Radio
hustle and bustle increased
Viceroy of Governor-General
Louis Mountbatten was expected to arrive
Lord Mountbatten arrived in the evening
he was accompanied by Jawaharlal Nehru
and the leader of Sikhs, Sardar Baldev Singh
and for muslims, India's secessionist...
demanding separate nation,
Mohammed Ali Jinnah
It has been impossible to obtain
full agreement on any plan
that would preserve the unity of India
there can be no question of coercive any large areas in which one community
as a majority to live against their will under a government
in which another community has the majority
the only alternative to coercion...
is...
partition!
after independence, two separate countries will be formed...
this was declared by Viceroy Lord Mountbatten
and Congress approval was declared on radio by Jawaharlal Nehru
for Nehru, it was a very emotional subject
I'm not pleased with partitioning of India
but at this moment, it is only possible solution
any region of India existing separately from the union is very sorrowful to all
but still, I've arrived at this decision with long term view ahead
the proposed solution is acceptable
which united India we fought and worked for...
to keep India united by partitioning into two countries, was called the "Mountbatten Plan"
but, with this Mountbatten Plan, many people were going to be worried
about shattering and scattering of India
and division of India
who could see this
but then just one day after the declaration
this story took a big turn
June 4, 1947
Lord Mountbatten called for press conference at the Legislative Assembly/Parliament
and significance of this press conference could be estimated
from the fact that on June 3, Lord Mountbatten was preparing mock drill late night
300 reporters from all over the world assembled to ask Lord Mountbatten regarding the future of India
I sincerely mean it, when I say that power will be transferred completely by 1947
the date of transfer of power by Britain to India will be around August 1947
I've already bought my steamer ticket for Aug 15, so this will be date of transfer
this was shocking news because British were expected to leave India by June 1948
and now Mountbatten declared that within 72 days partitioning and independence will be completed
Independence date was certain now but a big question arose from this declaration
without the answer independence was worthless...
How many nations were being freed- 2 or 565?
15 August 1947
15 August 1947, two countries were becoming independent. 2 or 565?
these details are not usually found in history books
but just few days before independence
Mahatma Gandhi, Jawaharlal Nehru & Sardar Patel were facing two big problems
first one, how to stop communal violence?
and the second, how to prevent distortion of beauty of India's shape?
the reason for second problem was "Lapse of Paramountcy"
on one hand we thought that the British had united entire India
then how does the talk of 565 nation states come from?
actually, the British India included small, medium, big princely states totalling about 565
these states were indirectly governed by the British; some kings had their own laws, police, armies & even currencies
these states had accepted the eminence and superiority of British throne, called Paramountcy
so when British were leaving, they declared that this Paramountcy also ended